Guide to the William Holman Hunt Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
William Holman Hunt collection
1859-1899
GEN MSS 1129
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.21
(1 box)
The collection consists of thirty-seven autograph letters, signed, written by William Holman Hunt to friends and acquaintances including Walter Crane, Sir Fred A. Eaton, and Sir William Watson. The bulk of the letters are to British artist, illustrator and designer Frederic James Shields; also present are four graphite sketches by Shields of Hunt at work at his easel.
Hunt, William Holman, 1827-1910
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired from various sources, 1948-1976. Source information is recorded at the folder level in the contents list. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
William Holman Hunt (1827-1910)
English painter, and one of the founders of the Pre-Raphaelite Brotherhood.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of thirty-seven autograph letters written by William Holman Hunt to friends and acquaintances including Walter Crane, Sir Fred A. Eaton, and Sir William Watson. The bulk of the letters are to British artist, illustrator and designer Frederic James Shields; also present are four graphite sketches by Shields of Hunt at work at his easel.
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically.
Artists -- Great Britain; Sketches -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Artists -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Craik, George Lillie, 1837-1905; Crane, Walter, 1845-1915; Eaton, Fred. A. (Frederick Alexis); Hunt, William Holman, 1827-1910; Hunt, William Holman, 1827-1910 -- Portraits; Shields, Frederic, 1833-1911; Watson, William, 1858-1935
- Letters, 1859-1899; 9
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  - To "My dear William"; autograph letter, signed, 1859 Apr 28 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Custodial History
    Purchased from Blackwell on the Plain Fund, 1954.
  - To "Mr. Prescott"; autograph letter, signed, 1864 Mar 11 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Purchased from Arthur Rogers on the Phelps Fund, 1956.
  - To "My dear sir"; autograph letter, signed, 1875 Apr 7 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Gift of Robert F. Metzdorf, 1957.
  - To Frederic James Shields; 28 autograph letters, signed, and 1 autograph letter, 1879-1899 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Purchased from Maggs on the Plain Fund, 1954.
    General note
    Accompanied by four sketches by Shields of Hunt working at his easel.
  - To Walter Crane; autograph letter, signed, 1886 Aug 18 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Gift of Philip M. Neufeld in honor of George Alpert, 1961.
  - To Sir Fred A. Eaton; autograph letter, signed, 1887 Dec 15 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Purchased on the Library Associates Fund, 1973.
  - To Sir William Watson; autograph letter, signed, 1891 Sep 25 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Purchased from Symington on the Plain Fund, 1948.
  - To George Lillie Craik; autograph letter, signed, 1892 Jun 10 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    George Lillie Craik (1837–1905), nephew of the author George Lillie Craik.
    Purchased from John Wilson (Christie's sale, 23 Jun 1976, lot 207) on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1976.
  - To "Mrs. Whitwell"; autograph letter, signed, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Bequest of Ray L. Murphy, 1954.